## **Professional Summary of Srini Karlekar**

I am an accomplished information technology professional with 24 years of experience. I am skilled in all aspects of software development including analysis, architecture, development, integration, implementation of enterprise grade applications on cloud and on premise. I come with a strong track record of delivering successful technology solutions in the banking, mortgage, telecommunication's and logistics industries. I have extensive background in reengineering business processes, building high-availability systems, re-platforming mission-critical systems, designing and mapping technical capabilities to business functions, creating capability target architectures with multi-year roadmaps, developing API strategy for financial services, designing serverless architecture to reduce cost, building streaming architecture for fast data, designing event-driven messaging systems for responsiveness, decomposing monolithic enterprise applications to Microservices, building Devops platforms for continuous integration and deployment, designing machine-learning model sandboxes, data pipelines for data lakes etc. I have consistent employment & consulting history with respected companies in the finance, telecommunication, wireless, marketing and utility industries.

#### Leadership:

I am currently working as a Director of Software Engineering for Capital One. In the role of Divisional Architect, I am supporting the architecture function for a large portfolio of applications in the Risk, Anti-Money Laundering and Compliance groups. In this role, I am responsible for defining the capability target architecture for the risk & compliance portfolios, defining the migration strategy of the applications and services from on-premise to the cloud, helping define a multi-year roadmap for achieving the target state, defining the decomposition of technical capabilities into APIs, Microservices and grooming the Serverless strategy. I also provide cloud engineering guidance to the development teams, develop design patterns and identify common capabilities that can be used across the enterprise.

Before this, I worked as a senior manager and lead architect on a multi-million dollar initiative to re-platform the Loan Sourcing function of Fannie Mae. As part of this role, I have not only blueprinted the target state of Loan Sourcing platform, but also was responsible for designing a highly available, scalable and resilient SOA-based platform architecture and influenced the design of the Loan Acquisition ODS. I also stood up the DevOps practice for the Loan Sourcing strategic initiative in Fannie Mae.

As an Adjunct Professor in the School of Management at George Mason University, I was responsible for designing the curriculum for the MIS 330 – System Analysis & Design, course materials and teaching new techniques and approaches to developing systems more effectively & efficiently. As a member of the EMBA Alumni Advisory Committee at the School of Management in George Mason University, I was part of the team responsible for soliciting opinions and perspectives on issues of importance to the MBA experience and formulate recommendations and presenting to the EMBA board.

As a Director in the Technology Integration practice of Answerthink (NASDAQ: ANSR), I was responsible for providing enterprise architecture solutions to various clients ranging from dot com firms to Fortune 500 firms. This work required consulting with C-level executives and senior management at these firms to identify their needs and devise technology solutions to bridge the gaps. As a technical architect on various projects, I have ensured that the architecture of the system is consistent with the client's long-term strategic direction, ensuring all the performance, security, scalability, extensibility and manageability goals and business requirements are met.

#### **Delivery:**

I have served as a director of multidisciplinary teams, identifying objectives of the work based on an understanding of program and overall priorities, and setting project milestones and deadlines. I have worked with auditors and system security specialists to lead the implementation of policies and procedures in compliance to Sarbanes-Oxley and other regulations.

I have served as development manager on various multi-million dollar projects for large organizations including Fannie Mae, UBS Warburg, ABN-AMRO, Samsung, JM Family (Southeastern Toyota), Ariba, NFI Interactive Logistics, etc. In these roles, I oversaw teams to effectively translate functional specifications into solid, understandable, and maintainable technology solutions within budget and on time.

#### Management:

During my tenure at various organizations, I have managed staff to translate business requirements into system deliverables including architecture artifacts, design, code, testing and user training artifacts. To this effect, I have interviewed potential candidates, approved or rejected vendor applications, set work priorities, reviewed project plans, tested and approved work deliverables. In addition, I have conducted performance reviews for my staff, approved raises based on merit, etc.

42746 Ravenglass Drive, Ashburn, VA 20148.

703-772-7371 (cell) - skarlekar@yahoo.com - http://srini.karlekar.com - https://www.linkedin.com/in/srinikarlekar/

#### **Summary of Qualifications**

An accomplished I.T professional with 24 years' experience. Extensive background in cloud architecture, serverless technologies, event-based messaging systems, teaching, project management, object oriented design, data modeling, etc. Consistent employment & consulting history with respected consulting companies, finance, telecommunication, wireless, marketing and utility industries. Proven understanding of complex business undertakings requiring practical knowledge in the critical areas of business analysis, technology, operations, project management, group dynamics, and client relationship construction and maintenance.

#### **Objective**

I am seeking a position where I can manage & mentor the architecture, design and development efforts for public cloud initiatives.

#### **Systems Designed**

- Data Pipelines on Cloud
- Facial Recognition Systems
- Loan Origination Systems
- Web Services
- Messaging Systems
- Web Services
- Distributed Systems
- Community Portals
- Web Content Management
- Wireless Systems

- Cloud Sandboxes
- Loan Committing Systems
- Directory Services
- Logistics Systems
- Workflow Engines
- Carrier Access Billing SystemsOnline Procurement systems
- ETL Systems
- Pricing Systems

- Serverless Microservices
- Mortgage-backed Securities Systems
- Finance & Trading Systems
- Application Frameworks
- Data & Control Center Systems
- Data Conversion Systems
- Architectural Assessments
- Messaging Systems
- XML Pipeline Systems

#### **Professional Certifications**

- 1. AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate
- 2. Sun Certified Java Programmer
- 3. Sun Certified Enterprise Architect
- 4. ITIL Foundation Certified
- 5. Certified Scrum Master

#### **Education**

# Master of Business Administration (EMBA), 2004-2006

(Global Capital Markets, Entrepreneurship & Change Management) 54 Credits (3.95 GPA, Summa Cumme Laude).

School of Management, George Mason University, Virginia.

Certificate in International Business Environment, 2006

Residency at Oxford University, Oxford, UK

Master of Science in Computer Applications, 1992

A.C.College of Engineering and Technology, Madurai Kamraj University, India.

**Bachelor of Science in Mathematics**, 1989

Madras University, India.

#### **Professional Publications & Seminars**

## Webinar: Building Microservices on AWS Using Serverless Framework

Cloud Academy, Aug 24, 2017

In this webinar, I describe the advantages of Serverless Architectures and distinguish it from the Serverless Framework. I then went on to demonstrate the Serverless Framework by building an application that will recognize faces of celebrities from images sent using SMS and respond with their name and biography. Attendees learnt how to use Twilio to process SMS/MMS messages, use Boto3 Python library to interface with AWS Rekognition and build services using the Serverless framework. <a href="http://bit.ly/slsCaWbnr">http://bit.ly/slsCaWbnr</a>

## Speaking Engagement: Building Event-driven Microservices using Serverless Framework

DevfestDC - A Google Developer's Conference, May 6, 2017

During this workshop I demonstrated building event-driven microservices built on top of AWS Lambda, Twilio, Amazon Rekognition and IMDbPy API using the Serverless framework. The service will take images of celebrities sent by SMS/MMS, match them and send their name and biography back via SMS.

Srini Karlekar ii

42746 Ravenglass Drive, Ashburn, VA 20148.

703-772-7371 (cell) - skarlekar@yahoo.com - http://srini.karlekar.com - https://www.linkedin.com/in/srinikarlekar/

Participants learnt how to use Twilio to process SMS/MMS messages, use Boto3 Python library to interface with AWS Rekognition and build services using the Serverless framework. The workshop started with the demonstration of the application and dove into building the application. Active participants created accounts with Twilio and AWS to follow along and built the clone.

## Designed & Delivered Undergraduate Course: MIS 330 System, Analysis & Design

George Mason University, August, 2009 – Jan 2011

Developed curriculum, course material and taught the course, MIS 330 – System, Analysis & Design at School of Mgmt, George Mason University, VA.

### **Professional Experience Summary**

# Director of Software Engineering, Risk, AML & Compliance Tech – Capital One (NYSE:COF), May 31st 2016 – Present

1680 Capital One Drive, McLean, VA 22102

Enterprise Divisional Architect responsible for driving the architecture for Risk, AML & Compliance group of Capital One using open source technologies & public cloud.

- Responsible for developing the Capability Target Architecture providing a multi-year view of the conceptual architecture spanning multiple applications across the Risk Tech portfolio.
- Using technology & market trends to create technology plans for the Risk Tech portfolio.
- Responsible for communicating a clear and concise overview of the architecture for the individual projects.
- Responsible for identifying common capabilities across the enterprise, while understanding adoption requirements, maturity requirements and advocating usage of such capabilities where appropriate.
- Responsible for evangelizing Cloud-Native and Serverless Architecture, Engineering Standards and Procedures that support the Enterprise Architecture Policy.
- Documenting patterns for building data pipelines in the cloud, API strategies, usage of streaming data and touch points across such technical capabilities.
- Leading teams in building proof-of-concepts to vet out new technologies and tools.
- Leading or assisting teams in portfolio planning and road mapping exercises.

Technology Stack: Various AWS Technologies, Python, Java, Spark etc.

# Senior Manager, Customer Engagement – Fannie Mae (NYSE:FNM), June 2003 – April, 2016 13100 Worldgate Drive, Herndon, VA 20170

As a Lead Architect and Development Manager on a multi-million dollar initiative to re-platform the Loan Sourcing function of Fannie Mae using Agile methodology, I led multiple teams to not only design the blueprint of the Loan Sourcing platform, but was also responsible for the overall technical architecture, development and deployment of the Loan Delivery Platform, Business Rules Orchestrator and other satellite systems. I have also influenced the design of the Acquisition Data Store and developed working prototypes to prove out architectural patterns including but not limited to the Business Rules Orchestrator, Reference Data Vending Utility, Enrichment Utility, Auto Screen Generator etc. These patterns are reducing the time to market for introducing new functionality into these Loan Sourcing platform.

Previously as a Portfolio Architect in the Customer Engagement division at Fannie Mae, I was responsible for designing solutions that aligns with the target state architecture of Fannie Mae. To this end, I was responsible for creating and owning the level 1,2 & 3 architecture artifacts, work closely with the business architecture team to ensure the architecture of the applications in my space maps to the business roadmap. In addition, I was responsible for partnering with the development teams and guiding them to work towards the target state architecture, champion development teams through the architecture review process, identify and leverage common services, contribute to the data architecture, participate in local data governance, data quality and contribute to various center of excellence. I also worked closely with management to identify and recommend opportunities to build, buy or integrate COTS products, common services and partner with the business to assist in the creation of blue prints.

*Technology Stack*: Java, Spring, Spring Integration, MongoDB, Oracle XML DB, Hibernate, J2EE (EJB, JMS), XML, XSLT, Weblogic AS, MQ Series, TIBCO, Oracle, Sybase, Rational Rose, Apache Ivy etc.

Srini Karlekar iii

42746 Ravenglass Drive, Ashburn, VA 20148.

703-772-7371 (cell) - skarlekar@yahoo.com - http://srini.karlekar.com - https://www.linkedin.com/in/srinikarlekar/

### Adjunct Professor, School of Management, GMU, Fairfax, VA Aug 2009 – Jan 2011

As an Adjunct faculty in the School of Management at George Mason University, I am responsible for designing the curriculum for the MIS 330 – System Analysis & Design, course materials and teaching new techniques and approaches to developing systems more effectively & efficiently. In addition, as part of the EMBA Alumni Advisory committee, I am responsible for providing advise and perspective on issues pertinent to the MBA experience, curriculum and alumni activities.

# Director – Technology Integration, Answerthink, Inc (NASDAQ:ANSR) Dec 1999 – Apr 2003 225, Washington Street, Conshohocken, PA 19428

As a Director in the Technology Integration practice of Answerthink, I was responsible for providing enterprise and application architecture solutions to various client projects and client management, conduct technical seminars, perform annual performance reviews to direct reports, lead and mentor a team of developers and technical leads to design & develop J2EE solutions.

As a Technical Architect on various projects, I ensured that the architecture of the system is consistent with the clients' long-term strategic direction while ensuring the performance, security, scalability, extensibility and manageability goals and business requirements are met. I worked with the support unit to set the strategy for production support, back-ups, disaster recovery, system performance, and project management. I was also responsible for obtaining stakeholder buy-in for application and technical designs and ensuring the deliverables are meeting the quality and traceability requirements.

Role, Initiative & Clients listed below chronologically with the most recent at the top:

- ♦ Architect & DBA Equity Plus System, UBS Warburg, Switzerland.
- Development Manager Amice Fund System, ABN-AMRO, Amsterdam.
- ♦ Development Manager & Architect Janus Pricing Subsystem, JM Family, South-Eastern Toyota, Boca Raton, Florida.
- Architect & Lead Developer Physician Pocket Chart Wireless App, Answerthink, Conshohocken, PA.
- Development Manager & Architect Directory Services Implementation, Enterprise Services, Airclic Inc, Philadelphia, PA.
- Architect Architecture Assessment Team, Fusura Inc, Wilmington, Delaware.
- ◆ Development Manager & Architect Deals Capture Management System, UBS Warburg, Switzerland.
- Development Manager & Architect Logistics & Web Services App, NFI Interactive Logistics, New Jersey.
- ◆ Architect & Lead Developer Tower Mapping & Information System, Crown Castle Inc, Philadephia.
- Development Manager Securities Trading System, Samsung Securities, Seoul, Korea.

# Senior Managing Consultant, Software Architects Inc. Tampa, FL. Jan 1995 – Dec 1999

As a Senior Managing Consultant with Software Architects (currently Sogeti USA), I was responsible for providing technology consulting services to various clients. Services included design and development of web-based procurement systems for Tradex (now Ariba), data mapping and conversions for telecom and marketing firms, online marketplace for a large energy trading company and a Carrier Access Billing System for a large telecom firm.

Role, Initiative & Client listed below in chronological order:

- Lead Developer, Professional Services Team, Tradex (now Ariba), Tampa, Florida.
- Lead Developer, Data Conversion Team, Catalina Marketing, St. Petersburg, Florida.
- ◆ Lead Developer, Data Conversion Team, Intermedia Communications, St. Petersburg, Florida.
- Architect & Lead Developer, Online Marketplace, Halliburton NUS Information Services, Clearwater, Florida.
- ♦ Lead Developer, Carrier Access Billing System, GTE Data Services, Tampa, Florida.

Srini Karlekar iv

42746 Ravenglass Drive, Ashburn, VA 20148.

703-772-7371 (cell) - skarlekar@yahoo.com - http://srini.karlekar.com - https://www.linkedin.com/in/srinikarlekar/

Senior Systems Analyst, Computer People, New York City, NY.

Jun 1994 - Dec 1994

Lead Developer - Solomon Brothers, New York City, NY.

Developed an on-line arbitrage system for trade capture, pricing, risk management, financial management, reporting and operational adjustments.

Systems Analyst, Sai Systems International Inc. Bridgeport, CT.

Sep 1993 - Jun 1994

Lead Developer - United Parcel Services R&D, Danbury, CT.

Designed and Re-engineered an OCR system from single threaded structural code to multi-threaded object-oriented system. Designed and coded the GUI & neural network functions for various components of the package address block OCR system for identifying address contents in the image.

Senior Systems Analyst, Nucleus Software Workshop, India.

Jun 1992 - Sep 1993

Lead Developer - Citibank N.A. Data Center Development, Madras, India.

Designed and developed EOD GUI-based automation tools for firing and monitoring EOD jobs, GUI based wrappers and adapters for wrapping VMS based email system in X-Windows. Developed various other X-Windows based utilities for use in the data center and managed resources.

Consultant, Maruthu Pandyirar Transport Corporation. Karaikudi, India Aug 1991 – Jan 1992

Developer - Retirement Fund Development Team, Karaikudi, India.

Designed and developed the provident and family fund packages.

#### SOFTWARE SKILLS - PROJECT RELATED

Cloud Providers: AWS, Azure, Google Cloud

**Application Servers:** Node.js, tcServer, JBOSS, WebLogic (Oracle),

Messaging Systems: Kafka, AWS SNS, AWS SQS, AWS Kinesis, TIBCO, MQ Series Databases: PostgreSQL, Redshift, MongoDB, Oracle XMLDB, Sybase, MySQL.

**Development:** Python, Java (Spring, Spring Integration, Hibernate, Struts, SOAP, REST, J2ME, MIDP, J2EE - RMI, EJB, JMS, JAXP, JSP, JNDI), Javascript, Angular is, Maven, ANT, LDAP, XML, C, C++, Oracle, PL/SQL, HTML,

Java Script, X-Windows, Xview, Motif, Tcl, Tk, Visual Basic, VB Script

Srini Karlekar v